[SPEAKER_00]: Again, this is the Anguttara.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhu is possessing three qualities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhu is practicing the unmistaken way, and has laid the groundwork for the destruction of the taints.
[SPEAKER_00]: What three?
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, Bhikkhu guards the doors of the sense faculties, observes moderation in eating, and is intent on wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, having seen a form with the eye, Bhikkhu does not grasp its marks and features, since if he left the eye-faculty unrestrained, bad, unwholesome states of longing and dejection might invade him.
[SPEAKER_00]: He practices
[SPEAKER_00]: Restraint over it, he guards the I-faculty, he undertakes the restraint of the I-faculty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having heard a sound of the ear, having smelt an odor with the nose, having tasted a taste with the tongue, having felt a tactile object with the body, having cognized the mental phenomenon with the mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: Abhikṣu does not grasp at its marks and features, since if he left the mind-faculty unrestrained, bad, unwholesome states of longing and dejection might invade him.
[SPEAKER_00]: He practices restraint over it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He guards the mind-faculty.
[SPEAKER_00]: He undertakes the restraint of the mind-faculty.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is in this way that Abhikṣu guards the doors of the sense-faculties.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in terms of sense-restraint, that seems to be the... that's the groundwork to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Begin practicing the Subha Meditation, wanting to be free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that you don't, you don't necessarily have, you don't, well, at all have to go and seek out beautiful objects and then practice the sasuga that you're talking about, meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is practice sensuous dreams.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the whole, the whole mind is already geared towards the mistake of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you're not actively seeking things with your senses, the mind and the thoughts and the way of attending, it's already implying sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you don't need to go and prove to yourself or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to keep restraining until the knowledge in regard to the nature of sensuality as fundamentally unattractive develops.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, of course, you won't have to prove anything, because you've done it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you go beyond senses, when you lose any form of concern with them, towards them, including concern of proving that you're free from concern in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if a thought comes up and the image of something that you're attracted to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Which will inevitably happen, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order for those thoughts of sensuality to become apparent, the actual senses must be well restrained beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the vinaya, the sīla comes first and that whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you're saying is to see the... to actually see the signs and features of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because sensuality is rooted in those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're not seeing those thoughts, because you're immediately out with the senses, seeking the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the whole point of restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, really, unwavering restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you don't give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you do, you're undermining your own clarity in regard to your own sensual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, every time you give in, you sort of induce more obscurity that you have to undo later.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, like, seeing the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know how hard it is to purify it, and then, how hard it is to maintain it pure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, that purity is necessary for any sort of insight that you can develop in regard to the root of sensuality, which is the level of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want your thoughts, sensual thoughts, to become apparent, to be seen through, as founded upon the unattractive, the senses, the actual senses, must be fully restrained beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then the mind becomes clearer, the mind affected with sensuality, the sensual intent and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Aureal will, the same, becomes clearer when the body and the senses have been restrained beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is absolutely never a reason to give in to non-restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's non-restraint, means it's not done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, just restraining senses in itself will not result in you understanding sensuality either.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to know what to look for, how to look for, what I described in the previous talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to see the unattractive basically in the heart of everything that's attractive, always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, attractive cannot step and become independent from unattractive.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't see that, then, yeah, sense restraint is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then your mind will probably develop in some
[SPEAKER_01]: In various ways, but not to the point of, like, the right view and the freedom from sensuality and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: For that, you need a bit more.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, none of that would be available, to be developed more, if you... if you don't have the sense restraint beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, if this essential thought arises, and you pick up the signs and features of that essential thought, you want to see that that essential thought... No matter what signs or features would be picked up, you also want to maintain the perception of inherent foundations of disgust.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter where your mind goes, left or right, with those signs and features and prospects and possibilities, the unwavering perception of... it's still very much always within the container of unattractive disgust.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop assuming the external to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop making it independent from any disgust, which is when the mind gets pulled by essential craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean, like, you have to see it simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like going... like a method, a succession of steps or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you restrain the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's as much as a method as you're going to get.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, don't... negative method, in a sense, if you don't engage with the sensuality through your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yes, when the mind inevitably thinks sensual thoughts, images, memories, the signs and features of something beautiful that accidentally came across a sound, a smell, a sight, and so on,
[SPEAKER_01]: If the sensor is strained, then that you have a groundwork now, which is the level of those thoughts that are picking up sensual signs.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to basically learn how to simultaneously see the inseparable basis of disgust in regard to any possibility of those sensual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not this thought, that thought, or this particular thought, any.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just entirely in its nature, in its domain, it's fully inseparable from the unattractive.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's rooted in it, inconceivable from.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you get to know it, to discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you don't have to keep doing anything, because whenever sensuality arises, it arises with its disgusting heart.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't want it, like, at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even in your imagination anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you would also understand that all the sensuality that has been in the past, that you did engage in, all the sensuality that you would have engaged in, it's still the same, same nature, same everything, cannot step outside of this basis, a vessel of disgust that's fully contained in.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, slightly different topic, but in the same sense, how Atavada ceases when you see that external to the five aggregates is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, no matter what self-view you might have, what conceit, it's fully contained within the arisen experience as a whole, which is the experience of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you fully discern that, you will eventually stop assuming any external dimension to it, which is basically the definition of Atavāda, a self that's external, that's independent of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's the same principle in regard to assuming the external, beautiful, independent of the foundation of the ugly, of not wanted, of dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why both are on the level of upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: The vādā and sensual desire.